Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 4: Maternal Physiology.
Reproductive Tract Breasts Skin Metabolic Changes Hematological Changes Cardiovascular System Respiratory Tract Urinary System Gastrointestinal Tract Endocrine System Musculoskeletal System Central Nervous System References The anatomical, physiological, and biochemical adaptations of pregnancy are profound.
Many gestational changes begin soon after fertilization and continue throughout pregnancy.
Equally astounding is the almost complete return to the prepregnancy state after delivery and lactation.
Most pregnancyrelated changes are prompted by stimuli provided by the fetus and placenta.
Virtually every organ system undergoes alterations, and these can appreciably modify criteria for disease diagnosis and treatment.
Thus, an understanding of pregnancy adaptations is essential to avoid misinterpretation.
Moreover, some normal physiological changes can unmask or worsen preexisting disease.
Reproductive Tract.
# Uterus.
In the nonpregnant woman, the uterus weighs approximately 70 g and is almost solid, except for a cavity of 10 mL or less.
During pregnancy, the uterus is transformed into a thin-walled muscular organ of sufficient capacity to accommodate the fetus, placenta, and amnionic fluid.
The total volume of the contents at term averages 5 L but may be 20 L or more!
Thus, by the end of pregnancy, the uterus has achieved a capacity that is 500 to 1000 times greater than the nonpregnant state.
The corresponding increase in uterine weight is such that, by term, the organ weighs nearly 1100 g. Uterine hypertrophy early in pregnancy is probably stimulated by the action of estrogen and perhaps progesterone.
Thus, similar uterine changes can be observed with ectopic pregnancy.
But after approximately 12 weeks’ gestation, uterine growth is related predominantly to pressure exerted by the expanding products of conception.
Within the uterus, enlargement is most marked in the fundus.
The extent of uterine hypertrophy is also influenced by the position of the placenta.
Namely, the myometrium surrounding the placental site grows more rapidly than does the rest.
During pregnancy, uterine enlargement involves stretching and marked hypertrophy of muscle cells, whereas the production of new myocytes is limited.
Fibrous tissue also accumulates, particularly in the external muscle layer, together with a considerable rise in elastic tissue content.
The walls of the corpus considerably thicken and strengthen during the first few months of pregnancy but then gradually thin.
By term, the myometrium is only 1 to 2 cm thick, and the fetus usually can be palpated through the soft, readily indentable uterine walls.
The uterine musculature during pregnancy is arranged in three strata.
The first is an outer hoodlike layer, which arches over the fundus and extends into the various ligaments.
The middle layer is a dense network of muscle fibers perforated in all directions by blood vessels.
Last is an internal layer, with sphincter-like fibers around the fallopian tube orifices and internal cervical os.
Most of the uterine wall is formed by the middle layer.
Here, each myocyte has a double curve so that the interlacing of any two cells forms a figure eight.
This crucial arrangement permits myocytes to contract after delivery and constrict penetrating blood vessels to halt bleeding.
Uterine Shape and Position For the first few weeks, the uterus maintains its original piriform or pear shape.
But, as pregnancy advances, the corpus and fundus become globular and almost spherical by 12 weeks’ gestation.
Subsequently, the organ grows more rapidly in length than in width and becomes ovoid.
By the end of 12 weeks, the enlarged uterus extends out of the pelvis.
With growth, it contacts the anterior abdominal wall, displaces the intestines laterally and superiorly, and ultimately reaches almost to the liver.
As it ascends, the uterus usually rotates to the right, and this dextrorotation likely is caused by the rectosigmoid on the left side of the pelvis.
As the uterus rises, tension is exerted on the
broad and round ligaments.
With the pregnant woman standing, the longitudinal axis of the uterus corresponds to an extension of the pelvic inlet axis.
The abdominal wall supports the uterus and maintains this axis, unless the wall is lax.
When the pregnant woman lies supine, the uterus falls back to rest on the vertebral column and the adjacent great vessels.
Uterine Contractility Beginning in early pregnancy, the uterus contracts irregularly, and these may be perceived as mild cramps.
During the second trimester, these contractions can be detected by bimanual examination.
In 1872, J. Braxton Hicks first brought attention to these contractions, which now bear his name.
These appear unpredictably and sporadically.
Their intensity varies between 5 and 25 mm Hg .
Until near term, these Braxton Hicks contractions are infrequent, but their number rises during the last week or two.
At this time, the uterus may contract as often as every 10 to 20 minutes and with some degree of rhythmicity.
Correspondingly, uterine electrical activity is low and uncoordinated early in gestation but becomes progressively more intense and synchronized by term .
This synchrony develops twice as fast in multiparas compared with nulliparas .
Late in pregnancy, these contractions may cause some discomfort and account for so-called false labor (Chap 21, p. 401).
Uteroplacental Blood Flow The delivery of most substances essential for fetal and placental growth, metabolism, and waste removal requires the placental intervillous space to be adequately perfused .
Placental perfusion depends on total uterine blood flow, but simultaneous measurement of uterine, ovarian, and collateral vessels is not yet possible, even using magnetic resonance (MR) angiography .
For this measurement, early results using fourdimensional flow MR imaging in the primate are promising .
Doppler ultrasound interrogation of the uterine arteries shows a progressive increase in uteroplacental blood flow during pregnancy.
Flow rates rise from approximately 450 mL/min in the midtrimester to nearly 500 to 750 mL/min at 36 weeks’ gestation (Flo, 2014; Wilson, 2007).
These measures are similar to flow estimates ascertained indirectly using clearance rates of androstenedione and xenon-133 (Edman, 1981; Kauppila, 1980).
These values also mirror older ones—500 to 750 mL/min—obtained with invasive methods (Assali, 1953; Metcalfe, 1955).
Logically, such massively increased uteroplacental blood flow requires adaptation of the uterine veins as well.
The resulting increased venous caliber and distensibility can result in uterine vein varices that rarely may rupture .
As noted first from animal studies, uterine contractions, either spontaneous or induced, lower uterine blood flow proportionally to contraction intensity .
A tetanic contraction yields a precipitous fall in uterine blood flow.
In humans, three-dimensional power Doppler angiography has also demonstrated reduced uterine blood flow during contractions .
Using a similar technique, resistance to blood flow in both maternal and fetal vessels was found to be greater during the second stage of labor compared with the first .
Given that baseline uterine blood flow is diminished in pregnancies complicated by fetal-growth restriction, these fetuses often tolerate spontaneous labor less effectively .
Uteroplacental Blood Flow Regulation The vessels that supply the uterine corpus widen and elongate yet preserve their contractile function .
As an exception, the spiral arteries, which directly supply the placenta, vasodilate but completely lose contractility.
This presumably stems from endovascular trophoblast invasion, which destroys the intramural muscular elements .
This vasodilation allows maternal–placental blood flow to progressively rise during gestation.
Given that blood flow increases proportionally to the fourth power of the radius of the vessel, small widening of a vessel diameter results in tremendous augmentation of flow.
In one study, the uterine artery diameter grew from only 3.3 mm to 3.7 mm between 22 and 29 weeks’
gestation, but mean blood flow velocity increased 50 percent, from 29 to 43 cm/sec .
The downstream fall in vascular resistance is another key factor that accelerates flow and shear stress in upstream vessels.
In turn, shear stress leads to circumferential vessel growth.
Nitric oxide—a potent vasodilator— appears to play a central role in regulating this process and is discussed later (p. 65).
Endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS) and nitric oxide production are augmented by endothelial shear stress and several hormones and growth factors (Osol, 2019; Zhang, 2017).
Factors include estrogen, progesterone, activin, placental growth factor (PlGF), and vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), which is a promoter of angiogenesis.
As an important aside, VEGF and PlGF signaling is attenuated in response to excess placental secretion of their soluble receptor—soluble FMS-like tyrosine kinase 1 (sFlt-1).
An elevated maternal sFlt-1 level inactivates and lowers circulating PlGF and VEGF concentrations and is important in preeclampsia pathogenesis .
Normal pregnancy is also characterized by vascular refractoriness to the pressor effects of infused angiotensin II, and this raises uteroplacental blood flow .
Other factors that augment uteroplacental blood flow include relaxin and certain adipocytokines .
Chemerin is an adipocytokine secreted by several tissues, including the placenta .
Its concentration rises as gestation advances and serves to increase human umbilical eNOS activity .
Another adipocytokine—visfatin—raises VEGF secretion and VEGF receptor 2 expression in epithelial cells derived from the placental amnion .
Other adipocytokines include leptin, resistin, and adiponectin, which all enhance umbilical vein endothelial cell proliferation (Połeć, 2014).
Last, certain microRNA species mediate vascular remodeling and uterine blood flow early in placentation .
In particular, members of the miR-17–92 cluster and miR-34 are important in spiral artery remodeling and invasion.
Micro-RNA dysfunction has been reported in preeclampsia, fetalgrowth restriction, and gestational diabetes.
# Cervix.
As early as 1 month after conception, the cervix begins to soften and gain bluish tones.
These changes result from increased vascularity and edema of the entire cervix, from alterations in the collagen network, and from hypertrophy and hyperplasia of the cervical glands .
Although the cervix contains a small amount of smooth muscle, its major component is connective tissue.
Rearrangement of this collagen-rich tissue aids the cervix in retention of the pregnancy until term, in dilation to aid delivery, and in postpartum repair and reconstitution to permit a subsequent successful pregnancy .
As detailed in Chapter 21 (p. 405), cervical ripening involves connective tissue remodeling that lowers collagen and proteoglycan concentrations and raises water content compared with the nonpregnant cervix.
Cervical glands undergo marked proliferation, and by the end of pregnancy, they occupy up to one half of the entire cervical mass.
This normal pregnancy-induced change prompts an extension, or eversion, of the proliferating columnar endocervical glands onto the ectocervical portio .
This tissue appears red and velvety and bleeds even with minor trauma, such as with Pap smear testing.
Figure 4-1.
Cervical eversion of pregnancy as viewed through a colposcope.
The eversion represents columnar epithelium on the portio of the cervix.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Claudia Werner.
The endocervical mucosal cells produce copious amounts of tenacious mucus that obstructs the cervical canal soon after conception .
This mucus is rich in immunoglobulins and cytokines and may act as an immunological barrier to protect the uterine contents against infection .
At labor onset, if not before, this mucus plug is expelled, resulting in a bloody show.
Moreover, the cervical mucus consistency changes during pregnancy.
Specifically, in most pregnant women, as a result of progesterone, when cervical mucus is spread and dried on a glass slide, it
shows poor crystallization, termed beading.
In some gravidas, as a result of amnionic fluid leakage, an arborization of ice-like crystals, called ferning, is seen microscopically.
Histologically, basal cells near the squamocolumnar junction can be prominent in size, shape, and staining quality in pregnancy.
These changes are considered to be estrogen induced.
In addition, pregnancy is associated with both endocervical gland hyperplasia and hypersecretory appearance— the Arias-Stella reaction.
This cytologic change can make differentiating these from truly atypical glandular cells during Pap test evaluation particularly difficult .
# Ovaries.
Ovulation ceases during pregnancy, and maturation of new follicles is suspended.
The single corpus luteum functions maximally during the first 6 to 7 weeks of pregnancy—4 to 5 weeks postovulation.
Thereafter, it contributes relatively little to progesterone production.
As discussed in Chapter 66 (p. 1170), surgical removal of the corpus luteum before 7 weeks’ gestation prompts a rapid fall in maternal serum progesterone levels and spontaneous abortion .
In these cases, exogenous progesterone is necessary for pregnancy maintenance until placental function is sufficient.
After 7 weeks, however, corpus luteum excision ordinarily does not cause abortion.
An extrauterine decidual reaction on and just beneath the ovarian surface is common in pregnancy and is usually observed at cesarean delivery.
These appear as slightly elevated clear or red blisters or patches that bleed easily and may, on first glance, resemble freshly torn adhesions.
Similar decidual reactions are seen on the uterine serosa and other pelvic, or even extrapelvic, abdominal organs .
These areas arise from subcoelomic mesenchyme or endometriotic lesions that have been stimulated by progesterone.
They histologically appear similar to progestin-stimulated intrauterine endometrial stroma .
The enormous caliber of the ovarian veins viewed at cesarean delivery is startling.
Hodgkinson (1953) found that the diameter of the ovarian vascular pedicle increased during pregnancy from 0.9 cm to approximately 2.6 cm at term.
Again, recall that flow in a tubular structure increases exponentially as the diameter enlarges.
Relaxin This protein hormone is secreted by the corpus luteum, the decidua, and the placenta in a pattern similar to that of human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) .
Relaxin is also expressed in brain, heart, and kidney.
It is mentioned here because its secretion by the corpus luteum appears to aid many maternal physiological adaptations, such as remodeling of reproductive-tract connective tissue to accommodate labor .
Relaxin also appears important in initiating augmented renal hemodynamics, lowering serum osmolality, and increasing arterial compliance, which are all associated with normal pregnancy .
Despite its name, serum relaxin levels do not contribute to greater peripheral joint laxity or pelvic girdle pain during pregnancy (Aldabe, 2012; Marnach, 2003).
Theca-Lutein Cysts These benign ovarian lesions reflect exaggerated physiological follicle stimulation, which is termed hyperreactio luteinalis.
The resulting bilateral cystic ovaries are variably enlarged.
The reaction is usually linked to markedly elevated serum hCG levels.
Logically, theca-lutein cysts are found frequently with gestational trophoblastic disease (Fig. 13-3, p. 238).
They may also develop with the placentomegaly that can accompany diabetes, antiD alloimmunization, and multifetal gestation.
Hyperreactio luteinalis is associated with preeclampsia and hyperthyroidism, which may contribute to elevated risks for fetal-growth restriction and preterm birth (Lynn, 2013; Malinowski, 2015).
These cysts are also encountered in women with otherwise uncomplicated pregnancies.
In these cases, an exaggerated response of the ovaries to normal levels of circulating hCG is suspected (Sarmento Gonçalves, 2015).
Although usually asymptomatic, hemorrhage into the cysts can cause acute abdominal pain .
Maternal virilization may be seen in up to 30 percent of
women, however, virilization of the fetus has only rarely been reported.
Maternal findings that include temporal balding, hirsutism, and clitoromegaly are associated with massively elevated levels of androstenedione and testosterone.
The diagnosis typically is based on sonographic findings of bilateral enlarged ovaries containing multiple cysts in the appropriate clinical settings.
The condition is self-limited and resolves following delivery.
Its management was reviewed by Malinowski (2015) and discussed further in Chapter 66 (p. 1171).
# Fallopian Tubes.
The fallopian tube musculature, that is, the myosalpinx, undergoes little hypertrophy during pregnancy.
The epithelium of the endosalpinx somewhat flattens.
Decidual cells may develop in the stroma of the endosalpinx, but a continuous decidual membrane is not formed.
Rarely, a fallopian tube may twist during uterine enlargement, but this torsion is more common with comorbid paratubal or ovarian cysts (Lee, 2015; Macedo, 2017).
# Vagina and Perineum.
During pregnancy, greater vascularity and hyperemia develop in the skin and muscles of the perineum and vulva, and the underlying abundant connective tissue softens.
This augmented vascularity prominently affects the vagina and cervix and results in the violet color characteristic of the Chadwick sign.
Within the vagina, the considerably elevated volume of cervical secretions during pregnancy forms a somewhat thick, white discharge.
The pH is acidic and varies from 3.5 to 6.
This pH results from increased production of lactic acid by Lactobacillus acidophilus during metabolism of glycogen energy stores in the vaginal epithelium.
Pregnancy is associated with an elevated risk of vulvovaginal candidiasis, particularly during the second and third trimesters.
Higher infection rates may stem from immunological and hormonal changes and from greater vaginal glycogen stores .
The vaginal walls undergo striking changes in preparation for the distention that accompanies labor and delivery.
These include considerable epithelial thickening, connective tissue loosening, and hypertrophy of smooth muscle cells.
Pelvic Organ Prolapse Pelvic Organ Prolapse Quantification (POP-Q) scores and sonographic studies show that vaginal support changes across pregnancy.
In particular, vaginal lengthening, posterior vaginal wall and hiatal relaxation, increased levator hiatal area, and greater first-trimester vaginal elastase activity are all associated with uncomplicated spontaneous vaginal delivery .
The larger hiatal area persists in women who deliver vaginally compared with women delivering by prelabor or early-labor cesarean delivery.
However, all women show greater hiatal distensibility after delivery, which is potentially a factor in later pelvic floor dysfunction (Blomqvist, 2018; Friedman, 2019).
In women with existing apical vaginal prolapse, the cervix, and occasionally a portion of the uterine body, can protrude variably from the vulva during early pregnancy.
With further growth, the uterus usually rises above the pelvis and can draw the cervix up with it.
If the uterus persists in its prolapsed position, symptoms of incarceration may develop at 10 to 14 weeks’ gestation .
As a preventive measure, the uterus can be replaced early in pregnancy and held in position with a space-filling pessary.
Attenuation of anterior vaginal wall support can lead to prolapse of the bladder, that is, cystocele.
Associated urinary stasis can predispose to infection.
Pregnancy may also worsen coexistent stress urinary incontinence (SUI), likely because urethral closing pressures do not rise sufficiently to compensate for altered bladder neck support.
Urinary incontinence affects nearly 20 percent of women during the first trimester and nearly 40 percent during the third trimester.
Most cases stem from SUI rather than urgency urinary incontinence (Abdullah, 2016; Franco, 2014).
In primigravidas, maternal age greater than 30 years, obesity, smoking, constipation, and gestational diabetes mellitus are all risk factors associated with incontinence during
pregnancy .
Attenuation of posterior vaginal wall support can lead to rectocele, and a large defect may fill with feces.
Splinting, in which a finger is inserted into the vagina, can bolster posterior wall support to aid evacuation.
Occasionally, digital rectal disimpaction is needed.
Uncommonly during labor, fetal descent is blocked by a cystocele or rectocele.
Emptying by catheterization or enema and compressing the bulge with vaginal fingers will resolve the impasse.
Rarely, a large enterocele may bulge into the vagina to block descent.
Similarly, the hernia sac and its abdominal contents are gently reduced.
Breasts.
In early pregnancy, women often experience breast tenderness and paresthesias.
After the second month, the breasts grow in size, and delicate veins are visible just beneath the skin.
The nipples become considerably larger, more deeply pigmented, and more erectile.
After the first few months, a thick, yellowish fluid—colostrum—can often be expressed from the nipples by gentle massage.
During the same months, the areolae become broader and more deeply pigmented.
Scattered through each areola are several small elevations, the glands of Montgomery, which are hypertrophic sebaceous glands.
If breasts gain extensive size, skin striae similar to those observed in the abdomen may develop.
Rarely, breasts can become pathologically enlarged—referred to as gigantomastia—which may require consideration of postpartum bromocriptine and later surgical reduction (Rezai, 2015; Türkan, 2016).
For most, prepregnancy breast size and ultimate volume of breast milk do not correlate.
Multiple factors influence milk production and are discussed in Chapter 36 (p. 640).
Skin.
Skin changes are common, and Fernandes and Amaral (2015) described dermatological changes in more than 900 pregnant women.
They found at least one physiological cutaneous change in 89 percent of the women examined.
Dermatological pathologies during pregnancy are found in Chapter 65.
# Abdominal Wall.
Beginning after midpregnancy, reddish, slightly depressed streaks commonly develop in the skin.
These are called striae gravidarum or stretch marks.
In multiparas, glistening, silvery lines that represent the cicatrices of previous striae frequently coexist.
In one study of 800 primiparas, 70 percent developed striae gravidarum on their abdomen; 33 percent on their breasts; and 41 percent on their hips and thighs .
The strongest associated risk factors included younger maternal age, family history, and prepregnancy weight and weight gain during pregnancy.
The etiology of striae gravidarum is unknown, but aloe vera gel and almond oil decrease itching and may help to prevent progression .
Occasionally, the muscles of the abdominal walls do not withstand the tension of the expanding pregnancy.
As a result, rectus muscles separate in the midline, creating diastasis recti of varying extent.
If severe, a considerable portion of the anterior uterine wall is covered by only a layer of skin, attenuated fascia, and peritoneum to form a ventral hernia.
# Hyperpigmentation.
This develops in up to 90 percent of women and is usually more accentuated in those with darker complexion .
Of specific sites, the pigmented skin line in the midline of the anterior abdominal wall—the linea alba—takes on dark brown-black pigmentation to form the linea nigra.
Occasionally, irregular brownish patches of varying size appear on the face and neck, giving rise to chloasma or melasma gravidarum—the mask of pregnancy.
Pigmentation of the areolae and genital skin also may be accentuated.
After delivery, these pigmentary changes usually disappear or at least regress considerably.
Oral contraceptives may cause similar alterations .
The etiology of these pigmentary changes is incompletely understood, however, hormonal and genetic factors are implicated.
Levels of melanocytestimulating hormone, a polypeptide similar to corticotropin, are elevated remarkably throughout pregnancy, and estrogen and progesterone also are reported to have melanocyte-stimulating effects.
# Vascular
Changes.
Angiomas, called vascular spiders, are particularly common on the face, neck, upper chest, and arms.
These are minute, red skin papules with radicles branching out from a central lesion.
The condition is often designated as nevus, angioma, or telangiectasis.
Palmar erythema is encountered during pregnancy.
Both conditions lack clinical significance and disappear in most gravidas shortly after pregnancy.
They are likely the consequence of hyperestrogenemia.
In addition to these discrete lesions, increased cutaneous blood flow in pregnancy serves to dissipate excess heat generated by augmented metabolism.
# Hair Changes.
Throughout life, the human hair follicle undergoes a pattern of cyclic activity that includes periods of hair growth (anagen phase), apoptosis-driven involution (catagen phase), and a resting period (telogen phase).
Based on a study of 116 healthy pregnant women, the anagen phase lengthens during pregnancy and the telogen rate increases postpartum .
Neither is exaggerated in most gravidas, but excessive hair loss in the puerperium is termed telogen effluvium .
Metabolic Changes.
In response to the greater demands of the rapidly growing fetus and placenta, the pregnant woman undergoes numerous metabolic changes.
By the third trimester, maternal basal metabolic rate rises by 20 percent compared with that of the nonpregnant state .
This rate grows by an additional 10 percent in women with a twin gestation .
This is stratified as 85, 285, and 475 kcal/d during the first, second, and third trimesters, respectively .
Of note, Abeysekera and coworkers (2016) reported that women accrue fat mass during pregnancy despite the increased total energy expenditure and without significant change in energy intake.
This suggests more efficient energy storage.
Table 4-1.
Additional Energy Demands During Normal Pregnancya Most of the normal weight gain in pregnancy is attributable to the uterus and its contents, the breasts, and expanded blood and extravascular extracellular fluid volumes.
A smaller fraction results from metabolic alterations that promote accumulation of cellular water, fat, and protein, which are so-called maternal reserves.
The average weight gain during pregnancy approximates 12.5 kg or 27.5 lb, and this value has remained consistent across studies and over time (Hytten, 1991; Jebeile, 2016).
Weight gain is detailed in Table 4-2 and in Chapter 10 (p. 183) .
Table 4-2.
Weight Gain Based on Pregnancy-Related Components # Water Metabolism.
In pregnancy, greater water retention is normal and mediated in part by a drop in plasma osmolality of 10 mOsm/kg.
As shown in Figure 4-2, this decline develops in early pregnancy and is induced by a reset of osmotic thresholds for thirst and vasopressin secretion .
Relaxin and other hormones are thought to play a role .
Figure 4-2.
Mean values (black line) ± standard deviations (blue lines) for plasma osmolality (P osm) measured at weekly intervals in nine women from preconception to 16 weeks.
LMP = last menstrual period; MP = menstrual period.
Redrawn from Davison JM, Dunlop W. Renal hemodynamics and tubular function normal human pregnancy, Kidney Int 1980 Aug;18(2):152–161.
Maternal serum osmolality is significantly lower than umbilical arterial osmolality to favor water transport to the fetus .
At term, the water content of the fetus, placenta, and amnionic fluid approximates 3.5 L.
Another 3.0 L accumulates from expanded maternal blood volume and from uterus and breast growth.
Thus, the minimum amount of extra water that the average woman accrues during normal pregnancy approximates 6.5 L.
This corresponds to almost 15 lb. Demonstrable pitting edema of the ankles and legs is seen in most gravidas, especially at the day’s end.
This fluid accumulation may amount to a liter or so.
It results from greater venous pressure below the level of the uterus as a consequence of partial vena cava occlusion.
A decline in interstitial colloid osmotic pressure induced by normal pregnancy also favors edema late in pregnancy (Øian, 1985).
Longitudinal studies of body
composition show a progressive accumulation of total body water and fat mass during pregnancy.
These two components as well as initial maternal weight and weight gained during pregnancy are highly associated with neonatal birthweight .
As discussed in Chapter 51 (p. 905), “overnourished” women are more likely to deliver oversized neonates, even when glucose tolerant.
# Protein Metabolism.
The products of conception, the uterus, and maternal blood are relatively rich in protein rather than fat or carbohydrate.
At term, the normally grown fetus and placenta together weigh about 4 kg and contain approximately 500 g of protein, or about half of the total pregnancy increase.
The remaining 500 g is added to the uterus as contractile protein, to the breasts primarily in the glands, and to maternal blood as hemoglobin and plasma proteins.
Amino acid concentrations are higher in the fetal than in the maternal compartment and generally result from facilitated transport across the placenta .
This greater concentration is largely regulated by the placenta through an incompletely understood process .
In particular, placental transport is variable for individuals and for different amino acids.
For example, tyrosine is a conditionally essential amino acid in the preterm neonate but not in the fetus .
The placenta concentrates amino acids into the fetal circulation and is also involved in protein synthesis, oxidation, and transamination of some nonessential amino acids .
Maternal protein intake does not appear to be a critical determinant for birthweight among well-nourished women .
Still, recent data suggest that current recommendations for protein intake may be too low.
These guidelines are extrapolated from nonpregnant adults and may underestimate actual needs.
Stephens and colleagues (2015) prospectively analyzed maternal protein intake and metabolism.
They estimated average requirements of 1.22 g/kg/d of protein for early pregnancy and 1.52 g/kg/d for late pregnancy.
These levels are higher than the current recommendation of 0.88 g/kg/d. Dietary protein intake is discussed in Chapter 10 (p. 185).
# Carbohydrate Metabolism.
Normal pregnancy is characterized by mild fasting hypoglycemia, postprandial hyperglycemia, and hyperinsulinemia .
This elevated basal level of plasma insulin in normal pregnancy is associated with several unique responses to glucose ingestion.
Specifically, after an oral glucose meal, gravidas demonstrate prolonged hyperglycemia and hyperinsulinemia and a greater suppression of glucagon.
This cannot be explained by an increased metabolism of insulin because its half-life during pregnancy is not changed appreciably .
Instead, this response reflects a pregnancy-induced state of peripheral insulin resistance, which ensures a sustained postprandial supply of glucose to the fetus.
Indeed, insulin sensitivity in late normal pregnancy is 30 to 70 percent lower than that of nonpregnant women .
Figure 4-3.
Diurnal changes in plasma glucose and insulin in normal late pregnancy.
The mechanisms responsible for this reduced insulin sensitivity include numerous endocrine and inflammatory factors .
In particular, pregnancy-related hormones such as progesterone, placentally derived growth hormone, prolactin, and cortisol; cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor; and hormones derived from central adiposity, particularly leptin and its interplay with prolactin, all have a role in the insulin resistance of pregnancy.
Even so, insulin resistance is not the only factor to elevate postprandial glucose values.
Hepatic gluconeogenesis is augmented during both diabetic and nondiabetic pregnancies, particularly in the third trimester .
When fasting overnight, the pregnant woman changes from a postprandial state characterized by elevated and sustained glucose levels to a fasting state characterized by lower levels of plasma glucose and some amino acids.
Instead, plasma concentrations of free fatty acids, triglycerides, and cholesterol are higher in the fasting state.
This pregnancy-induced switch in fuels from glucose to lipids has
been called accelerated starvation.
Certainly, when fasting is prolonged in the pregnant woman, these alterations are exaggerated and ketonemia rapidly appears.
# Fat Metabolism.
The concentrations of lipids, lipoproteins, and apolipoproteins in plasma rise appreciably during pregnancy (Appendix, p. 1231).
Increased insulin resistance and estrogen stimulation during pregnancy are responsible for maternal hyperlipidemia.
Augmented lipid synthesis and food intake contribute to maternal fat accumulation during the first two trimesters.
Overweight women who have excessive gestational weight gain accrue fat mass .
In the third trimester, however, fat storage declines or ceases.
This is a consequence of enhanced lipolytic activity, and decreased lipoprotein lipase activity reduces circulating triglyceride uptake into adipose tissue.
This transition to a catabolic state favors maternal use of lipids as an energy source and spares glucose and amino acids for the fetus.
Maternal hyperlipidemia is one of the most consistent and striking changes of lipid metabolism during late pregnancy.
Triacylglycerol and cholesterol levels in very-low-density lipoproteins (VLDLs), low-density lipoproteins (LDLs), and high-density lipoproteins (HDLs) are increased during the third trimester compared with those in nonpregnant women .
After delivery, the concentrations of these lipids, lipoproteins, and apolipoproteins decline.
Breastfeeding drops maternal triglyceride levels but increases those of HDL cholesterol (HDL-C).
The effects on total cholesterol and LDL cholesterol levels are unclear .
Table 4-3.
Plasma Concentrations of Lipids Hyperlipidemia is theoretically a concern because it is associated with endothelial dysfunction.
That said, endothelium-dependent vasodilation responses actually improve across pregnancy .
This is partly because increased HDL-C concentrations likely inhibit LDL oxidation and thus protect the endothelium.
These findings suggest that the increased cardiovascular disease risk in multiparas may be related to factors other than maternal hypercholesterolemia.
# Leptin.
This peptide hormone is primarily secreted by adipose tissue in nonpregnant humans.
It plays a key role in body fat and energy expenditure regulation and in reproduction.
For example, leptin is important for implantation, cell proliferation, and angiogenesis .
Leptin deficiency is associated with anovulation and infertility, whereas certain leptin mutations cause extreme obesity .
Among normal-weight gravidas, serum leptin levels rise and peak during the second trimester and plateau until term in concentrations two to four times higher than those in nonpregnant women.
Among obese women, leptin levels correlate with adiposity .
In all cases, leptin levels fall after delivery, reflecting the significant amounts produced by the placenta .
Leptin participates in regulating energy metabolism during pregnancy.
Despite the rise in leptin concentrations during pregnancy, reduced leptin sensitivity to food intake during pregnancy has been described .
This “leptin resistance” may serve to promote energy storage during pregnancy and for later lactation.
Higher leptin levels during pregnancy may be disadvantageous under certain situations, such as maternal obesity.
Leptin functions as a proinflammatory cytokine in white adipose tissue, which may dysregulate the inflammatory cascade and lead to placental dysfunction in obese women .
In addition, abnormally elevated leptin levels have been associated with preeclampsia, gestational diabetes, and fetal distress (Rabiepoor, 2019; Taylor, 2015).
Fetal leptin is important for the development of several organs that include the pancreas, kidney, heart, and brain.
Fetal levels correlate with maternal body mass index and birthweight (Özdemir, 2020).
Lower levels are linked to fetal-growth restriction .
# Other Adipocytokines.
Dozens of hormones with metabolic and/or inflammatory functions are produced by adipose tissue.
Adiponectin is a peptide produced primarily in maternal fat but not in the placenta .
It may play a
role in early pregnancy to assure a source of glycogen for fetal energy .
Adiponectin levels inversely correlate with adiposity, and it acts as a potent insulin sensitizer.
Despite reduced adiponectin levels in women with gestational diabetes, directed assays are not useful for predicting diabetes development .
Ghrelin is a peptide secreted mainly by the stomach in response to hunger.
It cooperates with other neuroendocrine factors, such as leptin, in energy homeostasis.
Ghrelin is also expressed in the placenta and likely has a role in fetal growth and cell proliferation (González-Domínguez, 2016).
Visfatin is a peptide that was first identified as a growth factor for B lymphocytes but is mainly produced within adipose tissue.
Mumtaz and associates (2015) propose that elevated levels of visfatin and leptin impair uterine contractility.
Such findings may provide a physiological basis for the observation that maternal obesity raises the risk for dysfunctional labor.
# Electrolyte and Mineral Metabolism.
During normal pregnancy, nearly 1000 mEq of sodium and 300 mEq of potassium are retained .
The glomerular filtration rate of sodium and potassium is increased, but the excretion of these electrolytes is unchanged during pregnancy as a result of enhanced tubular resorption .
Although total accumulations of sodium and potassium are elevated, their serum concentrations are diminished slightly (Appendix, p. 1229).
Several mechanisms may explain these lower levels .
In the case of potassium, it possibly involves the expanded plasma volume of pregnancy.
With respect to sodium, osmoregulation is altered, and the threshold for arginine vasopressin release is lowered.
This promotes free water retention and diminished sodium levels.
Total serum calcium levels, which include both ionized and nonionized calcium, decrease during pregnancy.
This reduction follows lowered plasma albumin concentrations and in turn a consequent decline in the amount of circulating protein-bound nonionized calcium.
Serum ionized calcium levels, however, remain unchanged .
The developing fetus imposes a significant demand on maternal calcium homeostasis.
For example, the fetal skeleton accrues approximately 30 g of calcium by term, 80 percent of which is deposited during the third trimester.
This demand is largely met by a doubling of maternal intestinal calcium absorption mediated partly by 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3, the serum levels of which also are doubled.
These higher levels of vitamin D are possibly stimulated by a twofold rise in parathyroid hormone (PTH)-related peptide levels produced by several tissues including the placenta .
To help compensate, dietary intake of sufficient calcium is necessary to prevent excess depletion from the mother.
A list of all recommended daily allowances is found in Table 10-5 (p. 184).
This is especially important for pregnant adolescents, in whom bones are still developing .
Unfortunately, a lack of robust data prevents drawing firm conclusions regarding the utility of calcium and vitamin D supplements during pregnancy (Bi, 2018; Hofmeyr, 2018).
Serum magnesium levels also decline during pregnancy.
Compared with nonpregnant women, both total and ionized magnesium concentrations are significantly lower during normal pregnancy .
Serum phosphate levels lie within the nonpregnant range .
Although calcitonin is an important regulator of serum calcium and phosphate, the importance of calcitonin as it relates to pregnancy is poorly understood .
Iodine requirements increase during normal pregnancy for several reasons .
First, maternal thyroxine (T4) production rises to maintain maternal euthyroidism and to transfer thyroid hormone to the fetus prior to fetal thyroid functioning.
Second, fetal thyroid hormone production increases during the second half of pregnancy.
This contributes to greater maternal iodine requirements because iodine readily crosses the placenta.
Third, the primary route of iodine excretion is the kidney.
Beginning in early pregnancy, the iodine glomerular filtration rate increases by 30 to 50 percent.
In sum, because of greater thyroid hormone production, fetal iodine requirements, and augmented renal clearance, dietary iodine needs are higher during normal gestation .
Although the placenta has the ability to store iodine, whether this organ functions to protect the fetus from inadequate maternal dietary iodine is currently unknown.
Iodine deficiency is discussed later in this chapter (p. 72) and in Chapter 61 (p. 1097).
Extremely low or high maternal iodine intake may affect childhood neurodevelopment .
At the extreme, maternal supplements containing excessive iodine have been associated with congenital hypothyroidism.
This stems from autoregulation in the thyroid gland—known as the Wolff-Chaikoff effect—to curb T4 production in response to iodine overconsumption.
The serum levels of many of these minerals are listed in the Appendix (p. 1229).
With respect to most other minerals, pregnancy induces little change in their metabolism other than their retention in amounts equivalent to those needed for growth.
An important exception is the considerably greater requirement for iron, which is discussed subsequently .
Hematological Changes.
# Blood Volume.
The well-known hypervolemia associated with normal pregnancy averages 40 to 45 percent above the nonpregnant blood volume after 32 to 34 weeks’ gestation (Pritchard, 1965; Zeeman, 2009).
In some, accumulated volume rises only modestly, whereas in others blood volume nearly doubles.
A fetus is not essential, as augmented blood volume develops in some with hydatidiform mole.
The stimulus is not known, but it likely is related to renin and prorenin with its effects on sodium and water retention .
Simultaneously, vascular plasticity accommodates the larger blood volume .
Pregnancy-induced hypervolemia serves several functions.
First, it meets the metabolic demands of the enlarged uterus and its greatly hypertrophied vascular system.
It also provides abundant nutrients and elements to support the rapidly growing placenta and fetus.
The expanded intravascular volume protects the mother, and in turn the fetus, against the deleterious effects of impaired venous return in the supine and erect positions.
Last, it safeguards the mother against the adverse effects of parturition-associated blood loss.
Maternal blood volume begins to accrue during the first trimester.
By 12 menstrual weeks, plasma volume expands by approximately 15 percent compared with that prior to pregnancy .
Maternal blood volume grows most rapidly during the midtrimester, rises at a much slower rate during the third trimester, and reaches a plateau during the last several weeks of pregnancy .
Blood volume accrues even more dramatically in twin gestations.
Figure 4-4.
Blood volume expansion during pregnancy in twins (n = 10) and singletons (n = 40).
Data shown as medians.
During blood volume expansion, plasma volume and erythrocyte mass increase.
Although more plasma than erythrocytes is usually added to the maternal circulation, the increase in erythrocyte volume is considerable and averages 450 mL .
Moderate erythroid hyperplasia develops in the bone marrow, and the reticulocyte count is elevated slightly during normal pregnancy.
These changes are almost certainly related to the rise in maternal plasma erythropoietin levels (Appendix, p. 1227).
Because of great plasma augmentation, both hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit decline slightly during pregnancy.
As a result, whole blood viscosity decreases .
Hemoglobin concentration at term averages 12.5 g/dL, and in approximately 5 percent of women it is below 11.0 g/dL.
Thus, a concentration <11.0 g/dL, especially late in pregnancy, is considered abnormal and usually due to iron-deficiency anemia rather than pregnancy hypervolemia .
# Iron Metabolism.
The total iron content of normal adult women ranges from 2.0 to 2.5 g, or approximately half that found normally in men.
Most of this is incorporated in hemoglobin or myoglobin, and thus iron stores of normal young women approximate only 300 mg .
Although the lower iron levels in women may be partly due
to menstrual blood loss, other factors have a role.
One is hepcidin—a peptide hormone that functions as a homeostatic regulator of systemic iron metabolism .
As shown in Figure 45, hepcidin levels drop early in pregnancy (Hedengran, 2016a,b).
Lower hepcidin levels are associated with greater absorption of iron via ferroportin in enterocytes .
Lower hepcidin levels also augment iron transport into the fetus via ferroportin in syncytiotrophoblast.
Hepcidin levels rise with inflammation, but drop with iron deficiency and increased amount of several hormones, including testosterone, estrogen, vitamin D, and possibly prolactin .
Figure 4-5.
Hepcidin levels during pregnancy.
Blue data points are median values and crossbars are the 25th and 75th percentiles.
D is delivery and D + 1 and D + 2 are postpartum days 1 and 2.
Of the approximate 1000 mg of iron required for normal pregnancy, about 300 mg is actively transferred to the fetus and placenta, and another 200 mg is lost through various normal excretion routes, primarily the gastrointestinal tract.
These are obligatory losses and accrue even when the mother is iron deficient.
The average increase in the total circulating erythrocyte volume— about 450 mL—requires another 500 mg. Recall that each 1 mL of erythrocytes contains 1.1 mg of iron.
As shown in Figure 4-6, most iron is used during the latter half of pregnancy .
Thus, the iron requirement becomes large after midpregnancy and averages 6 to 7 mg/d .
In most women, this amount is usually not available from iron stores or diet.
If the nonanemic pregnant woman is not given supplemental iron, serum iron and ferritin concentrations decline after midpregnancy.
Moreover, the optimal rise in maternal erythrocyte volume will not develop, and the hemoglobin concentration and hematocrit will fall appreciably as plasma volume rises.
At the same time, fetal red cell production is not impaired because the placenta transfers iron even if the mother has marked iron-deficiency anemia.
In severe cases, we have documented maternal hemoglobin values of 3 g/dL, and at the same time, fetuses had hemoglobin concentrations of 16 g/dL.
The mechanisms of placental iron transport and regulation are complex (Koenig, 2014; McArdle, 2014).
Figure 4-6.
Estimated daily iron requirements during pregnancy in a 55-kg woman.
With normal vaginal delivery, at least 500 to 600 mL of blood is typically lost, and thus not all the maternal iron added in the form of hemoglobin is spent.
The excess hemoglobin iron postpartum becomes stored iron.
# Immunological Functions.
Pregnancy is associated with suppression of various humoral and cellmediated immunological functions .
This permits accommodation of the “foreign” semiallogeneic fetal graft that contains antigens of both maternal and paternal origin .
The tolerance that exists at the maternal-fetal interface remains a great unsolved medical mystery.
This tolerance is complex and involves certain immune system adaptations and crosstalk among the maternal microbiome, uterine decidua, and trophoblast.
In particular, areas of the uterus that were previously considered sterile are colonized with bacteria.
In most cases, these microbes are believed to be commensal and play a tolerizing and protective role.
Indeed, commensal organisms may inhibit the proliferation of certain pathogens.
Several reviewers have described these relationships (Mor, 2015; Racicot, 2014; Sisti, 2016).
One immune adaptation that promotes tolerance and protection at the maternal-fetal interface involves the expression of special major histocompatibility complex (MHC) molecules on the trophoblast.
Another immune adaptation that promotes tolerance stems from important changes in CD4 T lymphocyte subpopulations in pregnancy.
Specifically, immunity mediated by T-helper (Th) 1 cells shifts to Th2-mediated immunity.
An important antiinflammatory component of pregnancy involves suppression of Th1 and T-cytotoxic (Tc) 1 cells, which lower secretion of interleukin 2 (IL2), interferon α, and tumor necrosis factor (TNF).
In cervical mucus,
peak levels of immunoglobulins A and G (IgA and IgG) are significantly higher during pregnancy, and the immunoglobulin-rich cervical mucus plug creates a barrier to ascending infection (Hansen, 2014; Wang, 2014).
Similarly, IgG is transferred to the developing fetus in the third trimester as a form of passive immunity, ostensibly in anticipation of birth.
Immunoglobulins secreted into breast milk during lactation augment neonatal defenses against infection .
# Leukocytes and Lymphocytes.
Normal leukocyte counts during pregnancy can be higher than nonpregnant values, and upper values approach 15,000/μL (Appendix, p. 1227).
During labor and the early puerperium, values may markedly rise to attain levels ≥25,000/μL .
The cause is unknown, but the same response occurs during and after strenuous exercise.
The leukocytosis possibly represents the reappearance of leukocytes previously shunted out of active circulation.
The distribution of lymphocyte cell types also is altered during pregnancy.
Specifically, B lymphocytes numbers are unchanged, but the absolute numbers of T lymphocytes rise and create a relative increase.
Concurrently, the ratio of CD4 to CD8 T lymphocytes does not change (Kühnert, 1998).
# Inflammatory Markers.
Many tests performed to diagnose inflammation cannot be used reliably during pregnancy.
For example, leukocyte alkaline phosphatase levels— used to evaluate myeloproliferative disorders—are elevated beginning early in pregnancy.
The concentration of C-reactive protein, an acute-phase serum reactant, rises rapidly in response to tissue trauma or inflammation.
Median C-reactive protein levels in pregnancy and labor are higher than for nonpregnant women .
Of nonlaboring gravidas, 95 percent had levels measuring ≤1.5 mg/dL, and gestational age did not affect serum levels.
Another marker of inflammation, the erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR), is increased in normal pregnancy because of elevated plasma globulin and fibrinogen concentrations.
Complement factors C3 and C4 levels also significantly rise during the second and third trimesters .
Concentrations of procalcitonin, a normal precursor of calcitonin, are low to undetectable in midpregnancy but increase at the end of the third trimester and through the first few postpartum days .
Procalcitonin levels rise with severe bacterial infections but remain low in viral infections and nonspecific inflammatory disease.
However, measured levels poorly predict development of overt or subclinical chorioamnionitis after premature rupture of membranes (Thornburg, 2016; Tujula, 2018).
# Coagulation and Fibrinolysis.
During normal pregnancy, both coagulation and fibrinolysis are augmented but remain balanced to maintain hemostasis .
Evidence of activation includes increased concentrations of all clotting factors except factors XI and XIII .
Table 4-4.
Coagulation Factor Normal Values Across Pregnancy Of procoagulants, the level and rate of thrombin generation throughout gestation progressively increase .
In normal nonpregnant women, plasma fibrinogen (factor I) averages 300 mg/dL and ranges from 200 to 400 mg/dL.
During normal pregnancy, the fibrinogen concentration rises approximately 50 percent.
In late pregnancy, it averages 450 mg/dL, with a range from 300 to 600 mg/dL.
As discussed, this contributes greatly to the striking elevation in the erythrocyte sedimentation rate.
Also, levels of factor XIII—fibrin stabilizing factor—significantly drop as normal pregnancy advances .
Few studies describe thromboelastographic changes in normal pregnancy .
The end product of the coagulation cascade is fibrin formation, and the main function of the fibrinolytic system is to remove excess fibrin.
Tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) converts plasminogen into plasmin, which is the enzyme that promotes fibrinolysis.
It yields fibrin-degradation products such as D-dimers, and levels of these are increased in pregnancy .
Although somewhat conflicting, most evidence suggests that fibrinolytic activity is reduced in normal pregnancy .
As reviewed by Cunningham and
Nelson (2015), these changes favor fibrin formation.
Although this is countered by increased levels of plasminogen, the net result is that pregnancy is a procoagulant state.
Amnionic fluid is a potent activation of coagulation .
Such changes serve to ensure hemostatic control during pregnancy, particularly during delivery when a certain amount of blood loss is expected.
# Regulatory Proteins.
Several proteins are natural inhibitors of coagulation, including proteins C and S and antithrombin.
Inherited or acquired deficiencies of these and other natural regulatory proteins—collectively referred to as thrombophilias— account for many thromboembolic episodes during pregnancy.
They are discussed in Chapter 55 (p. 976).
Activated protein C, along with the cofactors protein S and factor V, functions as an anticoagulant by neutralizing the procoagulants factor Va and factor VIIIa.
During pregnancy, resistance to activated protein C grows progressively and is related to a concomitant drop in free protein S levels and greater factor VIII concentrations.
Between the first and third trimesters, activated protein C levels decline from 2.4 to 1.9 U/mL, and free protein S concentrations diminish from 0.4 to 0.16 U/mL (Cunningham, 2015; Walker, 1997).
Antithrombin levels drop by 13 percent between midpregnancy and term and fall 30 percent from this baseline until 12 hours after delivery.
By 72 hours after delivery, there is a return to baseline .
# Platelets.
In a study of more than 7000 women, and as shown in Figure 4-7, the average platelet count declined across pregnancy and returned to normal nonpregnant values by 4 to 12 weeks postpartum .
The platelet counts were lower for twin pregnancies.
Lower platelet concentrations are partially due to hemodilution.
In addition, platelet consumption is likely augmented and creates a greater proportion of younger and therefore larger platelets .
Further, clinically insignificant levels of several markers of platelet activation rise with gestational age but drop postpartum .
Because of splenic enlargement, an element of “hypersplenism,” may sequester and prematurely destroy platelets .
Figure 4-7.
Platelet counts in singleton and twin pregnancies determined during 1st, 2nd, and 3rd trimester, at delivery, and then at 4–12 weeks postpartum.
NP = nonpregnant.
Values are means and 95% confidence intervals.
# Spleen.
By the end of normal pregnancy, the spleen enlarges up to 50 percent compared with that in the first trimester .
Moreover, Gayer and coworkers (2012) found that splenic size was 68-percent greater compared with that of nonpregnant controls.
The cause of this splenomegaly is unknown, but it might follow the increased blood volume and/or the hemodynamic changes of pregnancy.
Cardiovascular System.
Changes in cardiac function become apparent during the first 8 weeks of pregnancy .
Cardiac output is increased as early as the fifth week and reflects a reduced systemic vascular resistance and an increased heart rate.
Compared with prepregnancy measurements, brachial systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, and central systolic blood pressure are all significantly lower 6 to 7 weeks from the last menstrual period .
The resting pulse rate rises approximately 10 beats/min during pregnancy.
Nelson and associates (2015) found that for both normal and overweight women, heart rate rose significantly between 12 and 16 weeks’ and between 32 and 36 weeks’ gestation.
Between weeks 10 and 20, plasma volume expansion begins, and preload rises.
This augmented preload results in a significantly larger left atrial volume and ejection fraction .
Ventricular performance during pregnancy is influenced by both the decline in systemic vascular resistance and changes in pulsatile arterial flow.
Multiple factors contribute to this overall altered hemodynamic function, which allows the physiological demands of the fetus to be met while maintaining maternal cardiovascular integrity .
These changes in stroke volume during the last half of pregnancy and the effects of maternal posture are
summarized in Figure 4-8 .
Bijl and colleagues (2019) offer a detailed review of methods to measure cardiac function in gravidas.
Figure 4-8.
Left ventricular stroke volume across pregnancy compared with 12-week postpartum (nonpregnant) values for normal-weight women in the supine and lateral positions.
# Heart.
As the diaphragm becomes progressively elevated, the heart is displaced to the left and upward and is rotated on its long axis.
As a result, the apex is moved somewhat laterally from its usual position and produces a larger cardiac silhouette in chest radiographs.
Furthermore, gravidas normally have some degree of benign pericardial effusion, which may enlarge the cardiac silhouette .
These factors make it difficult to precisely identify moderate degrees of cardiomegaly by simple radiographic studies.
Normal pregnancy induces some characteristic electrocardiographic (ECG) changes, and the most common is slight left-axis deviation due to the altered heart position.
Q waves in leads II, III, and avF and flat or inverted T waves in leads III and V1–V3 also may be seen .
During pregnancy, many of the normal cardiac sounds are modified.
These include: (1) an exaggerated splitting of the first heart sound and increased loudness of both components, (2) no definite changes in the aortic and pulmonary elements of the second sound, and (3) a loud, easily heard third sound .
In most gravidas, a systolic murmur is intensified during inspiration in some or with expiration in others.
Less often, a soft diastolic murmur can be noted transiently, and continuous murmurs arising from the breast vasculature may be heard (Fig. 52-1, p. 917).
Structurally, the expanding plasma volume seen during normal pregnancy is reflected by enlarging cardiac end-systolic and end-diastolic dimensions.
Concurrently, however, septal thickness or ejection fraction does not change.
This is because these dimensional changes are accompanied by substantive ventricular remodeling, which is characterized by left-ventricular mass expansion of 30 to 35 percent near term.
In the nonpregnant state, the heart is capable of remodeling in response to stimuli such as hypertension and exercise.
Such cardiac plasticity likely is a continuum that encompasses physiological growth as with exercise, and pathological hypertrophy as with hypertension (Hill, 2008; Osol, 2019).
Stewart and colleagues (2016) used cardiac MR imaging to prospectively evaluate cardiac remodeling during pregnancy.
Compared with the first trimester, left ventricular mass significantly grew beginning at 26 to 30 weeks’ gestation, and this continued until delivery .
This remodeling is concentric and proportional to maternal size for both normal and overweight women and resolved within 3 months of delivery.
Certainly for clinical purposes, ventricular function during pregnancy is normal, as estimated by the Braunwald ventricular function graph .
For the given filling pressures, cardiac output is appropriate and thus cardiac function during pregnancy is eudynamic.
Of the metabolic changes that occur in the heart during pregnancy, the efficiency of cardiac work—which is the product of cardiac output × mean arterial pressure—is estimated to rise by approximately 25 percent.
The associated increase in oxygen consumption is primarily accomplished via increased coronary blood flow rather than increased extraction .
Figure 4-9.
Left ventricular mass of normal-weight and overweight women across pregnancy compared with 12-week postpartum (nonpregnant) values.
Figure 4-10.
Relationship between left ventricular stroke work index (LVSWI), cardiac output, and pulmonary capillary wedge pressure (PCWP) in 10 normal pregnant women in the third trimester.
# Cardiac Output.
When measured in the lateral recumbent position at rest, cardiac output increases significantly beginning in early pregnancy.
It continues to rise and remains elevated during the remainder.
In a supine woman, a large uterus consistently compresses veins and diminishes venous return from the lower body.
It may also compress the aorta.
In
response, cardiac filling is limited, and cardiac output lessened.
Specifically, cardiac MR imaging shows that a woman rolling from her back onto her left side raises her cardiac output at 26 to 30 weeks’ gestation by approximately 20 percent and at 32 to 34 weeks by 10 percent (see Fig. 4-7).
Consistent with this, Simpson and James (2005) found that fetal oxygen saturation is approximately 10 percent higher if a laboring woman lies in a lateral recumbent position compared with supine.
Upon standing, cardiac output falls to the same degree as in the nonpregnant woman .
In multifetal pregnancies, compared with singletons, maternal cardiac output is augmented further by almost another 20 percent.
Ghi and coworkers (2015) used transthoracic echocardiography to show that first-trimester cardiac output with twins (mean 5.5 L/min) was more than 20 percent greater than postpartum values.
Cardiac output values in the second (6.3 L/min) and third (6.3 L/min) trimesters rose an additional 15 percent compared with first-trimester output.
Due to augmented preload, left atrial and left ventricular end-diastolic diameters also grow with twins .
The augmented heart rate and inotropic contractility imply that cardiovascular reserve is reduced in multifetal gestations .
During first-stage labor, cardiac output rises moderately.
During the second stage, with vigorous expulsive efforts, it is appreciably greater.
The pregnancy-induced increase is lost after delivery, at times dependent on blood loss.
# Hemodynamic Function in Late Pregnancy.
Clark and associates (1989) conducted invasive studies to measure hemodynamic function late in pregnancy .
Right heart catheterization was performed in 10 healthy nulliparas at 35 to 38 weeks’ gestation, and again at 11 to 13 weeks postpartum.
Late pregnancy was associated with the expected increases in heart rate, stroke volume, and cardiac output.
Systemic vascular and pulmonary vascular resistance both dropped significantly, as did colloid osmotic pressure.
Pulmonary capillary wedge pressure and central venous pressure did not change appreciably.
Thus, although cardiac output rises, left ventricular function as measured by stroke work index remains similar to the nonpregnant normal range (see Fig. 4-10).
Put another way, normal pregnancy is not a continuous “high-output” state .
Table 4-5.
Central Hemodynamic Changes in 10 Normal Nulliparous Women Near Term and Postpartum # Circulation and Blood Pressure.
Arterial pressure usually declines to a nadir at 24 to 26 weeks’ gestation and rises thereafter.
Diastolic pressure decreases more than systolic.
Changes in posture affect arterial blood pressure .
Brachial artery pressure when sitting is lower than that when in the lateral recumbent supine position .
Additionally, systolic blood pressure is lower in the lateral positions compared with either the flexed sitting or supine positions .
In approximately 10 percent of women, supine compression of the great vessels by the uterus causes significant arterial hypotension, sometimes referred to as the supine hypotensive syndrome.
Also when supine, uterine arterial pressure—and thus uterine blood flow—is significantly lower than that in the brachial artery.
Evidence to support whether this directly affects fetal heart rate patterns in uncomplicated low-risk pregnancies is conflicting (Armstrong, 2011; Ibrahim, 2015).
Similar changes can also be seen with hemorrhage or with spinal analgesia.
Figure 4-11.
Sequential changes (± SEM) in blood pressure throughout pregnancy in 69 women in supine (blue lines) and left lateral recumbent positions (red lines).
PP = postpartum.
Studies have assessed vascular compliance before pregnancy, during pregnancy, and postpartum (Morris, 2015; Osman, 2017).
Compared with healthy nonpregnant controls, significant declines in mean arterial pressure and arterial stiffness were observed between prepregnant and postpartum time periods.
These findings suggest that pregnancy confers a favorable effect on maternal cardiovascular remodeling.
The venous system is a
high-flow, low-resistance circulation during pregnancy .
While antecubital venous pressure remains unchanged, in the supine position, femoral venous pressure rises steadily, from approximately 8 mm Hg early in pregnancy to 24 mm Hg at term.
Venous blood flow in the legs is retarded except when the lateral recumbent position is assumed.
This tendency toward blood stagnation in the lower extremities during later pregnancy is attributable to occlusion of the pelvic veins and inferior vena cava by the enlarged uterus.
The elevated venous pressure returns to normal when the pregnant woman lies on her side and immediately after delivery.
These alterations contribute to the dependent edema frequently experienced and to development of hemorrhoids and varicose veins in the legs and vulva.
These changes also predispose to deepvein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism.
# Renin, Angiotensin II, and Plasma Volume.
The renin-angiotensin-aldosterone axis is intimately involved in blood pressure control via sodium and water balance.
All components of this system show increased levels in normal pregnancy.
Renin is produced by both the maternal kidney and the placenta, and greater amounts of renin substrate (angiotensinogen) are produced by both maternal and fetal liver.
Elevated angiotensinogen levels result, in part, from augmented estrogen production during normal pregnancy and are important in first-trimester blood pressure maintenance .
Gant and associates (1973) reported that nulliparas who remained normotensive became and stayed refractory to the pressor effects of infused angiotensin II.
Conversely, those who ultimately became hypertensive developed, but then lost, this refractoriness.
The diminished vascular responsiveness to angiotensin II may be progesterone related.
Placental growth factor (PlGF) also blunts this response .
Normally, pregnant women lose their acquired vascular refractoriness to angiotensin II within 15 to 30 minutes after the placenta is delivered.
Large amounts of intramuscular progesterone given during late labor delay this diminishing responsiveness.
# Cardiac Natriuretic Peptides.
At least two species of these—atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP) and brain natriuretic peptide (BNP)—are secreted by cardiomyocytes in response to chamber-wall stretching.
These peptides regulate blood volume by provoking natriuresis, diuresis, and vascular smooth-muscle relaxation.
In nonpregnant and pregnant patients, levels of BNP and of amino-terminal pro– brain natriuretic peptide (Nt pro-BNP), as well as newer analytes such as suppressor of tumorigenicity 2 (ST2), may be useful in screening for depressed left ventricular systolic function and determining chronic heart failure prognosis (Cunningham, 2019; Ker, 2018).
During normal pregnancy, plasma ANP and BNP levels are maintained in the nonpregnant range despite greater plasma volume .
In one study, median BNP levels were stable across pregnancy with values <20 pg/mL .
BNP levels are elevated in severe preeclampsia, and this may be caused by cardiac strain from increased afterload.
It would appear that ANP-induced physiological adaptations participate in extracellular fluid volume expansion and in the elevated plasma aldosterone concentrations characteristic of normal pregnancy.
# Prostaglandins.
Elevated prostaglandin production during pregnancy is thought to have a central role in control of vascular tone, blood pressure, and sodium balance.
Renal medullary prostaglandin E2 synthesis is markedly elevated during late pregnancy and is presumed to be natriuretic.
Levels of prostacyclin (PGI2), the principal prostaglandin of endothelium, also rise during late pregnancy.
PGI2 regulates blood pressure and platelet function.
It helps maintain vasodilation during pregnancy, and its deficiency is associated with pathological vasoconstriction .
The ratio of PGI2 to thromboxane in maternal urine and blood may be important indicators of preeclampsia pathogenesis.
# Endothelin.
Pregnancy generates several endothelins, which are vasoconstricting peptides.
Endothelin-1 is a
potent vasoconstrictor produced in endothelial and vascular smooth muscle cells and regulates local vasomotor tone .
Its production is stimulated by angiotensin II, arginine vasopressin, and thrombin.
Endothelins, in turn, stimulate secretion of ANP, aldosterone, and catecholamines.
Vascular sensitivity to endothelin 1 is not altered during normal pregnancy.
Pathologically elevated levels may play a role in preeclampsia .
# Nitric Oxide.
This potent vasodilator is released by endothelial cells and may modify vascular resistance during pregnancy.
As discussed earlier (p. 52), nitric oxide is an important mediator of placental vascular tone and development .
Abnormal nitric oxide synthesis has been linked to preeclampsia (Laskowska, 2015; Vignini, 2016).
Respiratory Tract.
Of anatomical changes, the diaphragm rises approximately 4 cm during pregnancy .
The subcostal angle widens appreciably as the transverse diameter of the thoracic cage lengthens approximately 2 cm.
The thoracic circumference increases about 6 cm, but not sufficiently to prevent reduced residual lung volumes created by the elevated diaphragm.
Even so, diaphragmatic excursion is greater in pregnancy.
Dyspnea is common .
Figure 4-12.
Chest wall measurements in nonpregnant (left) and pregnant women (right).
The subcostal angle increases, as does the anteroposterior and transverse diameters of the chest wall and chest wall circumference.
These changes compensate for the 4-cm elevation of the diaphragm so that total lung capacity is not significantly reduced.
Redrawn from Hegewald MJ, Crapo RO. Respiratory physiology in pregnancy, Clin Chest Med 2011 Mar;32(1):1–13.) # Pulmonary Function.
Of physiological lung changes, functional residual capacity (FRC) decreases by approximately 20 to 30 percent or 400 to 700 mL during pregnancy .
This capacity is composed of expiratory reserve volume—which drops 15 to 20 percent or 200 to 300 mL—and residual volume—which decreases 20 to 25 percent or 200 to 400 mL.
FRC and residual volume decline progressively across pregnancy due to diaphragm elevation.
Significant reductions are observed by the sixth month.
Inspiratory capacity, the maximum volume that can be inhaled from FRC, rises by 5 to 10 percent or 200 to 350 mL during pregnancy.
Total lung capacity—the combination of FRC and inspiratory capacity—is unchanged or declines by <5 percent at term .
Figure 4-13.
Changes in lung volumes with pregnancy.
The most significant changes are reduction in functional residual capacity (FRC) and its subcomponents, expiratory reserve volume (ERV) and residual volume (RV), as well as increases in inspiratory capacity (IC) and tidal volume (VT).
Reproduced with permission from Hegewald MJ, Crapo RO. Respiratory physiology in pregnancy, Clin Chest Med 2011 Mar;32(1):1–13.
The respiratory rate is essentially unchanged, but tidal volume and resting minute ventilation increase significantly as pregnancy advances.
Kolarzyk and coworkers (2005) reported significantly greater mean tidal volumes—0.66 to 0.8 L/min—and resting minute ventilations—10.7 to 14.1 L/min—compared with those of nonpregnant women.
The elevated minute ventilation is caused by several factors.
These include enhanced respiratory drive primarily due to the stimulatory action of progesterone, low expiratory reserve volume, and compensated respiratory alkalosis .
Also, decreased plasma osmolality can result in less respiratory depression .
Regarding pulmonary function, peak expiratory flow rates rise progressively as gestation advances .
Lung compliance is unaffected by pregnancy.
Airway conductance is increased and total pulmonary resistance reduced, possibly as a result of progesterone.
The maximum breathing capacity and forced or timed vital capacity are not altered appreciably.
It is unclear whether the critical closing volume—the lung volume at which airways in the dependent parts of the lung begin to close during expiration—is higher in pregnancy .
Pulmonary function with a singleton pregnancy does not significantly differ from that
with twins .
Importantly, the greater oxygen requirements and perhaps the increased critical closing volume imposed by pregnancy make respiratory diseases more serious.
Demir and colleagues (2015) studied nasal physiology in 85 pregnant women.
Although the minimal cross-sectional area decreased between the first and third trimesters, subjective reports of nasal congestion or total nasal resistance did not significantly differ among trimesters or compared with nonpregnant controls.
# Oxygen Delivery.
The amount of oxygen delivered into the lungs by the increased tidal volume clearly exceeds oxygen requirements imposed by pregnancy.
Moreover, the total hemoglobin mass and, in turn, total oxygen-carrying capacity rise appreciably during normal pregnancy, as does cardiac output.
Consequently, the maternal arteriovenous oxygen difference is diminished.
Oxygen consumption grows approximately 20 percent during pregnancy, and it is approximately 10 percent higher in multifetal gestations .
During labor, oxygen consumption increases 40 to 60 percent .
# Acid–Base Equilibrium.
A greater awareness of a desire to breathe is common even early in pregnancy .
This may be interpreted as dyspnea, which may suggest pulmonary or cardiac abnormalities when none exist.
This physiological dyspnea, which should not interfere with normal physical activity, is thought to result from greater tidal volume that lowers the partial pressure of carbon dioxide (CO2) in blood (PaCO2) slightly and paradoxically causes dyspnea.
The increased respiratory effort during pregnancy, and in turn the reduction in the PaCO2, is likely induced in large part by progesterone and to a lesser degree by estrogen.
Progesterone acts centrally.
Here, it lowers the threshold and raises the sensitivity of the chemoreflex response to carbon dioxide .
To compensate for the resulting respiratory alkalosis, plasma bicarbonate levels normally drop from 26 to 22 mmol/L.
Although blood pH is increased only minimally, it does shift the oxygen dissociation curve to the left.
This shift increases the affinity of maternal hemoglobin for oxygen—the Bohr effect—thereby lowering the oxygen-releasing capacity of maternal blood.
This is offset because the slight pH rise also stimulates an increase in 2,3diphosphoglycerate in maternal erythrocytes.
This shifts the curve back to the right .
Thus, reduced PaCO2 from maternal hyperventilation aids CO2 (waste) transfer from the fetus to the mother while also aiding oxygen release to the fetus.
Urinary System.
# Kidney.
The urinary system undergoes several remarkable changes in pregnancy .
Kidney size grows approximately 1.0 cm .
Both the glomerular filtration rate (GFR) and renal plasma flow increase early in pregnancy.
The GFR rises as much as 25 percent by the second week after conception and 50 percent by the beginning of the second trimester .
This hyperfiltration results from two principal factors.
First, hypervolemia-induced hemodilution lowers the protein concentration and oncotic pressure of plasma entering the glomerular microcirculation.
Second, renal plasma flow rises by approximately 80 percent before the end of the first trimester (Conrad, 2015; Lopes van Balen, 2019).
Elevated GFR persists until term, even though renal plasma flow declines during late pregnancy.
Primarily as a consequence of this elevated GFR, approximately 60 percent of nulliparas during the third trimester experience urinary frequency, and 80 percent experience nocturia .
Table 4-6.
Renal Changes in Normal Pregnancy Figure 4-14.
Glomerular filtration rate across pregnancy as measured by inulin clearance.
The solid line is the 50th percentile and the dashed lines are the 5th and 95th percentiles.
During the puerperium, a marked GFR persists during the first postpartum day, principally from the reduced glomerular capillary oncotic pressure.
The gestational hypervolemia and hemodilution, still evident on the first postpartum day, resolves by the second week postpartum.
Studies suggest that relaxin, discussed earlier (p. 54), may mediate both increased GFR
and renal blood flow during pregnancy .
Relaxin boosts renal nitric oxide production, which leads to renal vasodilation and lowered renal afferent and efferent arteriolar resistance.
This augments renal blood flow and GFR .
Relaxin may also increase vascular gelatinase activity during pregnancy, which leads to renal vasodilation, glomerular hyperfiltration, and reduced myogenic reactivity of small renal arteries .
As with blood pressure, maternal posture may considerably influence several aspects of renal function.
Late in pregnancy, the sodium excretion rate in the supine position averages less than half that in the lateral recumbent position.
The effects of posture on GFR and renal plasma flow vary.
One unusual feature of the pregnancy-induced changes in renal excretion is the remarkably higher amounts of some nutrients lost in the urine.
Amino acids and water-soluble vitamins are excreted in much greater amounts .
# Renal Function Tests.
The mean nonpregnancy serum creatinine level of 0.7 mg/dL declines during normal pregnancy to 0.5 mg/dL.
Values ≥0.9 mg/dL suggest underlying renal disease and prompt further evaluation.
Creatinine clearance in pregnancy averages 30 percent higher than the 100 to 115 mL/min in nonpregnant women.
This is a useful test to estimate renal function, provided that complete urine collection is made during an accurately timed period.
If this is not done precisely, results are misleading .
During the day, pregnant women tend to accumulate water as dependent edema.
When recumbent at night, they mobilize this fluid with diuresis.
This reversal of the usual nonpregnant diurnal pattern of urinary flow causes nocturia, and urine is more dilute than in nonpregnant women.
Failure of a pregnant woman to excrete concentrated urine after withholding fluids for approximately 18 hours does not necessarily signify renal damage.
In fact, the kidneys in these circumstances function perfectly normally by excreting mobilized extracellular fluid of relatively low osmolality.
# Urinalysis.
Glucosuria during pregnancy may not be abnormal.
The appreciably increased GFR, together with impaired tubular reabsorptive capacity for filtered glucose, accounts for most cases of glucosuria.
Chesley (1963) calculated that approximately one sixth of gravidas will spill glucose in the urine.
As discussed in Chapter 56 (p. 994), although the sensitivity is low, glucosuria may be an indicator of gestational diabetes mellitus.
For women with glucosuria, no guidelines in the United States direct practice, but in the United Kingdom, early oral glucose testing is considered for those with an isolated 2+ or repetitive 1+ urine dipstick readings .
Hematuria most often suggests urinary tract disease or infection.
Evaluation of this finding is outlined in Chapter 56 (p. 995).
Hematuria is common after difficult labor and delivery because of trauma to the bladder and urethra.
Proteinuria is typically defined in nonpregnant subjects as a protein excretion rate of more than 150 mg/d.
Because of the aforementioned hyperfiltration and possible reduction of tubular reabsorption, proteinuria during pregnancy is usually considered significant once a protein excretion threshold of at least 300 mg/d is reached .
Higby and coworkers (1994) measured protein excretion in 270 normal women throughout pregnancy .
Mean 24-hour excretion for all three trimesters was 115 mg, and the upper 95-percent confidence limit was 260 mg/d without significant differences by trimester.
They showed that albumin excretion is minimal and ranges from 5 to 30 mg/d. Proteinuria increases with gestational age, which corresponds with the peak in GFR .
Figure 4-15.
Scatter plot of women showing 24-hour urinary total protein excretion by gestational age.
Mean and 95-percent confidence limits are outlined.
Modified with permission from Higby K, Suiter CR, Phelps JY, et al: Normal values of urinary albumin and total protein excretion during pregnancy, Am J Obstet Gynecol 1994 Oct;171(4):984–989.
Measuring Urine Protein The three most commonly employed approaches for
assessing proteinuria are the qualitative classic dipstick, the quantitative 24-hour collection, and the albumin/creatinine or protein/creatinine ratio of a single voided urine specimen.
The pitfalls of each approach have been reviewed (Bramham, 2016; Conrad, 2015).
With dipstick assessment, the principal problem is its failure to account for renal concentration or dilution of urine.
For example, with polyuria and extremely dilute urine, a negative or trace dipstick could actually be associated with excessive protein excretion.
The 24-hour urine collection is affected by urinary tract dilation, discussed in the next section.
The dilated tract may lead to errors related both to retention—hundreds of milliliters of urine remaining in the dilated tract—and to timing—the remaining urine may have formed hours before the collection.
To minimize these pitfalls, the patient is first hydrated and positioned in lateral recumbency—the definitive nonobstructive posture—for 45 to 60 minutes.
After this, she is asked to void, and this specimen is discarded.
Immediately following this void, her 24-hour collection begins.
During the final hour of collection, the patient is again placed in the lateral recumbent position.
But, at the end of this hour, the final collected urine is incorporated into the total collected volume .
Last, the protein:creatinine ratio is a promising approach because data can be obtained quickly and collection errors are avoided.
Disadvantageously, the amount of protein per unit of creatinine excreted during a 24-hour period is not constant, and the thresholds to define abnormal vary.
Nomograms for urinary microalbumin and creatinine ratios during uncomplicated pregnancies have been developed.
The ratio is unreliable postpartum .
# Ureters.
After the uterus completely rises out of the pelvis, it rests on the ureters.
This laterally displaces and compresses them at the pelvic brim.
Above this level, elevated intraureteral tonus results, and ureteral dilation (hydroureter) and hydronephrosis is impressive.
It is greater on the right side as shown in Figure 4-16.
It is right sided in 86 percent of women.
This unequal dilation may result from cushioning provided to the left ureter by the sigmoid colon and perhaps from greater right ureteral compression exerted by the dextrorotated uterus.
The right ovarian vein complex, which is remarkably dilated during pregnancy, lies obliquely over the right ureter and may also contribute to ureteral compression and proximal dilation.
Figure 4-16.
Hydronephrosis.
Plain film from the 15-minute image of an intravenous pyelogram (IVP).
Moderate hydronephrosis on the right (arrows) and mild hydronephrosis on the left (arrowheads) are both normal for this 35-week gestation.
Progesterone likely has some additional effect.
Van Wagenen and Jenkins (1939) described continued ureteral dilation after removal of the monkey fetus but with the placenta left in situ.
The relatively abrupt onset of dilation in women at midpregnancy, however, seems more consistent with ureteral compression.
Ureteral elongation accompanies distention, and the ureter is frequently thrown into curves of varying size, and smaller curves may be sharply angulated.
These so-called kinks are poorly named, because the term connotes obstruction.
They are usually single or double curves that, when viewed in a radiograph taken in the same plane as the curve, may appear as acute angulations.
Another exposure at right angles nearly always identifies them to be gentle curves.
Despite these anatomical changes, complication rates associated with ureteroscopy in pregnant and nonpregnant patients do not differ significantly .
# Bladder.
The bladder shows few significant anatomical changes before 12 weeks’ gestation.
Subsequently, however, increased uterine size, the hyperemia that affects all pelvic organs, and hyperplasia of bladder muscle and connective tissues together elevate the trigone and thicken its intraureteric margin.
Continuation of this process to term produces marked deepening and widening of the
trigone.
The bladder mucosa is unchanged other than an increase in the size and tortuosity of its blood vessels.
Bladder pressure in primigravidas rises from 8 cm H2O early in pregnancy to 20 cm H2O at term .
To compensate for reduced bladder capacity, absolute and functional urethral lengths increase by 6.7 and 4.8 mm, respectively.
Concurrently, maximal intraurethral pressure rises from 70 to 93 cm H2O, and thus continence is maintained.
Still, at least half of women experience some degree of urinary incontinence by the third trimester .
Indeed, this is always considered in the differential diagnosis of ruptured membranes.
Near term—particularly in nulliparas, in whom the presenting part often engages before labor—the entire base of the bladder is pushed ventral and cephalad.
This converts the normally convex surface into a concavity.
As a result, diagnostic and therapeutic procedures are more difficult.
Moreover, pressure from the presenting part impairs blood and lymph drainage from the bladder base, often rendering the area edematous, easily traumatized, and possibly more susceptible to infection.
Gastrointestinal Tract.
As pregnancy progresses, the stomach and intestines are displaced cephalad by the enlarging uterus.
Consequently, the physical findings in certain diseases are altered.
The appendix, for instance, is usually displaced upward and somewhat laterally.
At times, it may reach the right flank.
Pyrosis (heartburn) is common during pregnancy and is most likely caused by reflux of acidic secretions into the lower esophagus.
Although the altered stomach position probably contributes to its frequency, lower esophageal sphincter tone also is diminished.
In addition, intraesophageal pressures are lower and intragastric pressures higher in pregnant women.
Concurrently, esophageal peristalsis has lower wave speed and lower amplitude .
Gastric emptying time is essentially unchanged across pregnancy in gravidas compared with nonpregnant women.
In fasting women at term, gastric volume is not different than that in nonpregnant controls .
At term, during labor, and especially after administration of analgesics, however, gastric emptying time may be appreciably prolonged .
As a result, one danger of general anesthesia for delivery is regurgitation and aspiration of either food-laden or highly acidic gastric contents.
Some reports describe maternal gut microbiome changes during pregnancy .
Currently, however, the vaginal and gut microbiome profiles and their influence on pregnancy are unclear .
Hemorrhoids are common during pregnancy .
They are caused in large measure by constipation and elevated pressure in rectal veins below the level of the enlarged uterus.
# Liver.
Liver size does not enlarge during human pregnancy.
Hepatic arterial and portal venous blood flow, however, rise substantively .
Liver stiffness increases from the second to third trimester and returns to baseline postpartum .
Some laboratory test results of hepatic function are altered in normal pregnancy (Appendix, p. 1229).
Total alkaline phosphatase activity almost doubles, but much of the rise is attributable to heat-stable placental alkaline phosphatase isozymes.
Serum aspartate transaminase (AST), alanine transaminase (ALT), γ-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT), and bilirubin levels are slightly lower compared with nonpregnant values .
The serum albumin concentration declines during pregnancy.
By late pregnancy, albumin levels may be near 3.0 g/dL compared with approximately 4.3 g/dL in nonpregnant women .
Total body albumin levels rise, however, because of pregnancy-associated expansion of plasma volume.
Serum globulin levels also are slightly higher.
Leucine aminopeptidase is a proteolytic liver enzyme whose serum levels may be elevated with liver disease.
Its activity is markedly higher in pregnant women.
The rise, however, results from a pregnancy-specific enzyme(s) with distinct substrate specificities .
Pregnancyinduced aminopeptidase has oxytocinase and vasopressinase activity that occasionally causes transient diabetes insipidus .
#
Gallbladder.
During normal pregnancy, gallbladder volume expands by approximately 50 percent, contractility declines, and both lead to greater residual volume .
Progesterone potentially impairs gallbladder contraction by inhibiting cholecystokinin-mediated smooth muscle stimulation, which is the primary regulator of gallbladder contraction.
Impaired emptying, subsequent stasis, and the greater cholesterol saturation of bile in pregnancy contribute to the increased prevalence of cholesterol gallstones in multiparas.
In one study, approximately 8 percent of women had gallbladder sludge or stones .
The pregnancy effects on maternal serum bile acid concentrations are still incompletely characterized.
This is despite the long-acknowledged propensity for pregnancy to cause intrahepatic cholestasis from retained bile salts.
Cholestasis of pregnancy is described in Chapter 58 (p. 1032).
Endocrine System.
# Pituitary Gland.
During normal pregnancy, the pituitary gland enlarges by approximately 135 percent .
This expansion may sufficiently compress the optic chiasma to reduce visual fields.
Impaired vision from this is rare and usually due to macroadenomas .
Pituitary enlargement is primarily caused by estrogen-stimulated hypertrophy and hyperplasia of the lactotrophs .
As discussed subsequently, maternal serum prolactin levels parallel this growth.
Gonadotroph number decline, and corticotroph and thyrotroph populations remain constant.
Somatotroph function is generally suppressed due to negative feedback by the placental production of growth hormone.
Peak pituitary size may reach 12 mm in MR images in the first days postpartum.
The gland involutes rapidly and reaches normal size by 6 months postpartum .
The incidence of pituitary prolactinomas is not increased during pregnancy.
When these tumors are large before pregnancy, such as with macroadenomas that by definition measure ≥10 mm, then growth during pregnancy is more likely .
The maternal pituitary gland is not essential for pregnancy maintenance.
Many women have undergone hypophysectomy, completed pregnancy successfully, and entered spontaneous labor while receiving compensatory glucocorticoids, thyroid hormone, and vasopressin.
Of pituitary gland hormones, growth hormone during the first trimester is secreted predominantly from the maternal pituitary gland, and concentrations in serum and amnionic fluid lie within the nonpregnant range.
As early as 6 weeks’ gestation, growth hormone secreted from the placenta becomes detectable, and by approximately 20 weeks, the placenta is the principal source of growth hormone secretion .
During this time, maternal serum values rise slowly from approximately 3.5 ng/mL at 10 weeks to plateau at about 14 ng/mL after 28 weeks’ gestation.
Growth hormone in amnionic fluid peaks at 14 to 15 weeks’ gestation and slowly declines thereafter to reach baseline values after 36 weeks.
Placental growth hormone—which differs from pituitary growth hormone by 13 amino acid residues—is secreted by syncytiotrophoblast .
Its regulation and physiological effects are incompletely understood, but it influences fetal growth via upregulation of insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1).
That said, fetal growth still progresses in the complete absence of this hormone.
Although not absolutely essential, the hormone may act in concert with placental lactogen to regulate fetal growth .
Prolactin levels rise markedly in maternal plasma during normal pregnancy.
Concentrations are usually tenfold greater at term—approximately 150 ng/mL—compared with those of nonpregnant women.
Paradoxically, plasma levels drop after delivery even in women who are breastfeeding.
During early lactation, pulsatile bursts of prolactin secretion are a response to suckling.
The principal function of maternal prolactin is to ensure lactation.
Early in pregnancy, prolactin acts to initiate DNA synthesis and mitosis of glandular epithelial cells and presecretory alveolar cells of the breast.
Prolactin also augments the number of estrogen and prolactin receptors in these cells.
Last,
prolactin promotes mammary alveolar cell RNA synthesis, galactopoiesis, and production of casein, lactalbumin, lactose, and lipids .
A woman with isolated prolactin deficiency failed to lactate after two pregnancies .
This establishes prolactin as a requisite for lactation but not for pregnancy.
Grattan (2015) has reviewed the numerous physiological roles of prolactin to aid maternal adaptations to pregnancy.
The prolactin receptor in the maternal pancreas indicates that prolactin may function to mediate pancreatic adaptations to pregnancy .
A possible role is proposed for a prolactin fragment in the genesis of peripartum cardiomyopathy (Cunningham, 2019; Koenig, 2018).
Prolactin is present in amnionic fluid in high concentrations.
Levels of up to 10,000 ng/mL are found at 20 to 26 weeks’ gestation.
Thereafter, levels decline and reach a nadir after 34 weeks.
Uterine decidua is the synthesis site of amnionic fluid prolactin.
The exact function of this hormone is unknown, but water transfer from the fetus into the maternal compartment to prevent fetal dehydration is one suggestion.
Oxytocin and antidiuretic hormone are hormones secreted from the posterior pituitary gland.
The roles of oxytocin in parturition and lactation are discussed in Chapters 21 (p. 413) and 36 (p. 640), respectively.
Brown and colleagues (2013) have reviewed the complex mechanisms that promote quiescence of oxytocin systems during pregnancy.
Levels of antidiuretic hormone, also called vasopressin, do not change during pregnancy.
As discussed earlier (p. 56), osmolality is slightly higher in maternal compared with fetal blood, and the gradient favors water transport to the fetus .
# Thyroid Gland.
The maternal and fetal thyroid glands are intricately interrelated.
On the maternal side, thyrotropin-releasing hormone (TRH) is secreted by the hypothalamus and stimulates thyrotrope cells of the anterior pituitary to release thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), also called thyrotropin.
TRH levels do not rise during normal pregnancy.
However, TRH does cross the placenta and may serve to stimulate the fetal pituitary to secrete TSH.
Serum TSH and hCG levels vary with gestational age .
As discussed in Chapter 5 (p. 96), the α-subunits of the two glycoproteins are identical, whereas the β-subunits, although similar, differ in their amino acid sequence.
As a result of this structural similarity, hCG has intrinsic thyrotropic activity, and thus, high serum hCG levels cause thyroid stimulation.
Indeed, TSH levels in the first trimester decline in more than 80 percent of pregnant women, however, they still remain in the normal range for nonpregnant women.
Figure 4-17.
Relative changes in maternal and fetal thyroid function across pregnancy.
Maternal changes include a marked and early increase in hepatic production of thyroxine-binding globulin (TBG) and placental production of human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG).
Elevated TBG increases serum thyroxine (T4) concentrations.
hCG has thyrotropin-like activity and stimulates maternal free T4 secretion.
This transient hCG-induced increase in serum T4 levels inhibits maternal secretion of thyrotropin.
Except for minimally increased free T4 levels when hCG peaks, these levels are essentially unchanged.
Fetal levels of all serum thyroid analytes increase incrementally across pregnancy.
Fetal triiodothyronine (T3) does not increase until late pregnancy.
The thyroid gland boosts production of thyroid hormones by 40 to 100 percent to meet maternal and fetal needs .
To accomplish this, the thyroid gland undergoes moderate enlargement during pregnancy caused by glandular hyperplasia and greater vascularity.
Mean thyroid volume expands from 12 mL in the first trimester to 15 mL at term .
That said, normal pregnancy does not typically cause significant thyromegaly, and thus any goiter warrants evaluation.
Early in the first trimester, levels of the principal carrier protein— thyroid-binding globulin (TBG)—rise.
They reach their zenith at about 20 weeks’ gestation.
Concentrations stabilize at approximately double
baseline values for the remainder of pregnancy (see Fig. 4-17).
The greater TBG concentrations result from both higher hepatic synthesis rates—due to estrogen stimulation—and lower metabolism rates due to increased TBG sialylation and glycosylation.
These elevated TBG levels increase total serum T4 and triiodothyronine (T3) concentrations, but do not affect the physiologically important serum free T4 and free T3 levels.
Specifically, total serum T4 levels rise sharply beginning between 6 and 9 weeks’ gestation and reach a plateau at 18 weeks.
Serum free T4 levels rise only slightly and peak along with hCG levels, and then they return to normal.
Interestingly, T4 and T3 secretion is not similar for all pregnant women.
Approximately a third of women experience relative hypothyroxinemia, preferential T3 secretion, and higher, albeit normal, serum TSH levels .
Thus, thyroidal adjustments during normal pregnancy may vary considerably.
The fetus relies on maternal T4, which crosses the placenta in small quantities to maintain normal fetal thyroid function .
Recall that the fetal thyroid does not begin to concentrate iodine until 10 to 12 weeks’ gestation.
The synthesis and secretion of thyroid hormone by fetal pituitary TSH ensues at approximately 20 weeks.
At birth, approximately 30 percent of the T4 in umbilical cord blood is of maternal origin .
Thyroid Function Tests As detailed in Chapter 61 (p. 1095), a substantial proportion of otherwise normal pregnancies are found to have subclinical hypothyroidism or isolated hypothyroxinemia.
The effects of thyroxine replacement in these women is currently controversial .
Normal suppression of TSH during pregnancy may lead to a misdiagnosis of subclinical hyperthyroidism.
Of greater concern is the potential failure to identify women with early hypothyroidism because of suppressed TSH concentrations.
To mitigate the likelihood of such misdiagnoses, Dashe and coworkers (2005), and others, have developed gestational-age-specific TSH normal curves for both singleton and twin pregnancies .
Figure 4-18.
Gestational age-specific thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) nomogram derived from 13,599 singleton pregnancies.
The nonpregnant reference values of 4.0 and 0.4 mU/L are represented as solid black lines.
Upper shaded area represents the 28 percent of singleton pregnancies with TSH values above the 97.5th percentile threshold that would not have been identified as abnormal based on the assay reference value of 4.0 mU/L. Lower shaded area represents singleton pregnancies that would have been (falsely) identified as having TSH suppression based on the assay reference value of 0.4 mU/L.
These complex alterations of thyroid regulation do not appear to alter maternal thyroid status as measured by metabolic studies.
Although basal metabolic rate rises progressively by as much as 25 percent during normal pregnancy, most of this greater oxygen consumption can be attributed to fetal metabolic activity.
If fetal body surface area is considered along with that of the mother, the predicted and observed basal metabolic rates are similar to those in nonpregnant women.
Iodine Status As discussed earlier (p. 59), iodine requirements increase during normal pregnancy .
In women with low or marginal intake, deficiency may manifest as low T4 and higher TSH levels.
Importantly, more than one third of the world population lives in areas where iodine intake is marginal.
Even in modernized countries, iodine deficiency is commonplace .
For the fetus, early exposure to thyroid hormone is essential for the nervous system.
Yet, despite public health programs to supplement iodine, severe deficiency that results in cretinism affects more than 2 million people globally .
# Parathyroid Glands.
During pregnancy, levels of calcitriol, which is the bioactive form of vitamin D, increase twofold and enhance intestinal calcium absorption .
In an earlier longitudinal investigation of 20 women, all markers of bone turnover rose during normal pregnancy and failed to reach baseline levels by 12 months postpartum .
Investigators concluded that the calcium needed for fetal growth and lactation may be drawn at least in part from the maternal skeleton.
The factors affecting bone turnover create a net yield that favors fetal skeletal formation at the expense of the mother.
As a result, pregnancy is a vulnerable period for osteoporosis .
Parathyroid hormone (PTH) release is stimulated by acute or chronic declines in plasma calcium or acute drops in magnesium levels.
Conversely, greater calcium and magnesium levels suppress PTH levels.
The action of this hormone on bone resorption, intestinal absorption, and kidney reabsorption is to raise extracellular fluid calcium concentrations and lower phosphate levels.
As discussed earlier (p. 59), fetal skeleton mineralization requires approximately 30 g of calcium, primarily during the third trimester.
Although this amounts to only 3 percent of the total calcium held within the maternal skeleton, calcium demands still challenge the mother .
Augmented maternal calcium absorption provides the additional calcium.
During pregnancy, the amount of calcium absorbed rises gradually and reaches approximately 400 mg/d in the third trimester.
Greater calcium absorption appears to be mediated by elevated maternal 1,25dihydroxyvitamin D concentrations.
This occurs despite decreased PTH levels during early pregnancy, which is the normal stimulus for active vitamin D production within the kidney.
Indeed, PTH plasma levels decline during the first trimester and then rise progressively throughout the remainder of pregnancy .
The increased production of active vitamin D is likely due to placental production of either PTH or a PTH-related protein (PTH-rP).
Outside pregnancy and lactation, PTH-rP is usually detectable only in serum of women with hypercalcemia due to malignancy.
During pregnancy, however, PTH-rP concentrations rise significantly.
This protein is synthesized in both fetal tissues and maternal breasts.
Calcitonin is secreted by C cells that are located predominantly in the perifollicular areas of the thyroid gland.
Calcitonin opposes actions of PTH and vitamin D and protects the maternal skeleton during times of calcium stress.
As discussed, pregnancy and lactation cause profound maternal calcium stress.
Indeed, fetal calcitonin levels are at least twofold higher than maternal levels .
Although maternal calcitonin levels fall during pregnancy, they generally rise postpartum.
Calcium and magnesium promote the biosynthesis and secretion of calcitonin.
Various gastric hormones—gastrin, pentagastrin, glucagon, and pancreozymin—and food ingestion also promote calcitonin plasma levels.
# Adrenal Glands.
Cortisol In normal pregnancy, unlike their fetal counterparts, the maternal adrenal glands undergo little, if any, morphological change.
The serum concentration of circulating cortisol rises, but much of it is bound by transcortin, the cortisol-binding globulin.
The adrenal secretion rate of this principal glucocorticoid is not elevated, and it is probably lower than in the nonpregnant state.
The metabolic clearance rate of cortisol, however, is diminished during pregnancy because its half-life is nearly doubled compared with that for nonpregnant women .
Administration of estrogen, including most oral contraceptives, causes changes in serum cortisol levels and transcortin similar to those of pregnancy .
During early pregnancy, the levels of circulating adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH ), also known as corticotropin, are dramatically reduced.
As pregnancy progresses, ACTH and free cortisol levels rise equally and strikingly .
This apparent paradox is not understood completely.
Some suggest that greater free cortisol levels in pregnancy result from a “resetting” of the maternal feedback mechanism to higher thresholds .
This might result from tissue refractoriness to cortisol.
Others assert that these incongruities stem from an antagonistic action of progesterone on mineralocorticoids .
Thus, in response to elevated progesterone levels during pregnancy, an elevated free cortisol is needed to maintain
homeostasis.
Other theories include possible roles for higher free cortisol in preparation for the stress of pregnancy, delivery, and lactation.
Figure 4-19.
Serial increases in serum cortisol (blue line) and adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) (red line) across normal pregnancy.
Aldosterone As early as 15 weeks’ gestation, the maternal adrenal glands secrete considerably higher amounts of aldosterone, the principal mineralocorticoid.
By the third trimester, approximately 1 mg/d is released.
If sodium intake is restricted, aldosterone secretion is even further elevated.
Concurrently, levels of renin and angiotensin II substrate normally rise, especially during the latter half of pregnancy.
This scenario promotes greater plasma levels of angiotensin II, which acts on the zona glomerulosa of the maternal adrenal glands and accounts for the markedly elevated aldosterone secretion.
Some suggest the increased aldosterone secretion during normal pregnancy affords protection against the natriuretic effect of progesterone and atrial natriuretic peptide.
Gennari-Moser and colleagues (2011) provide evidence that aldosterone and cortisol may modulate trophoblast growth and placental size.
Deoxycorticosterone Maternal plasma levels of this potent mineralocorticosteroid progressively increase during pregnancy.
Indeed, plasma levels of deoxycorticosterone rise to near 1500 pg/mL by term, a more than 15-fold increase .
This marked elevation does not derive from adrenal secretion but instead represents augmented kidney production resulting from estrogen stimulation.
The levels of deoxycorticosterone and its sulfate in fetal blood are appreciably higher than those in maternal blood, which suggests transfer of fetal deoxycorticosterone into the maternal compartment.
Androgens In balance, androgenic activity rises during pregnancy, and both maternal plasma levels of androstenedione and testosterone are increased.
This finding is not totally explained by alterations in their metabolic clearance.
Both androgens are converted to estradiol in the placenta, which increases their clearance rates.
Conversely, greater plasma sex hormone–binding globulin levels in gravidas retard testosterone clearance.
Thus, the production rates of maternal testosterone and androstenedione during human pregnancy are increased.
The source of this higher C19-steroid production is unknown, but it likely originates in the ovary.
Interestingly, little or no testosterone in maternal plasma enters the fetal circulation as testosterone.
Even when massive testosterone levels are found in the circulation of pregnant women, as with androgen-secreting tumors, testosterone concentrations in umbilical cord blood are likely to be undetectable.
This results from the near complete trophoblastic conversion of testosterone to 17β-estradiol.
Maternal serum and urine levels of dehydroepiandrosterone sulfate are lower during normal pregnancy.
This stems from a greater metabolic clearance through extensive maternal hepatic 16α-hydroxylation and placental conversion to estrogen .
Musculoskeletal System.
Progressive lordosis is characteristic of pregnancy.
Compensating for the anterior position of the enlarging uterus, lordosis shifts the center of gravity dorsally and over the lower extremities.
The sacroiliac, sacrococcygeal, and pubic joints have greater mobility during pregnancy.
However, as discussed earlier, increased joint laxity and associated discomfort during pregnancy do not correlate with increased maternal serum levels of estradiol, progesterone, or relaxin.
Most relaxation takes place in the first half of pregnancy.
It may contribute to maternal posture alterations and in turn create lower back discomfort.
As discussed in Chapter 36 (p. 644), although some symphyseal separation likely accompanies many deliveries, those greater than 1 cm may cause significant pain .
Aching, numbness, and weakness also occasionally are experienced in the upper extremities.
This may result from the marked lordosis and associated anterior neck flexion and shoulder girdle slumping.
These
can produce traction on the ulnar and median nerves.
The latter may give rise to symptoms mistaken for the carpal tunnel syndrome .
Joint strengthening begins immediately following delivery and is usually complete within 3 to 5 months.
Pelvic dimensions measured by MR imaging up to 3 months postpartum are not significantly different from prepregnancy values .
Central Nervous System.
Changes to the central nervous system during pregnancy are relatively few and mostly subtle.
Zeeman and coworkers (2003) used MR imaging to measure cerebral blood flow across pregnancy.
They found that mean blood flow in the middle and posterior cerebral arteries declined progressively from 147 and 56 mL/min when nonpregnant to 118 and 44 mL/min late in pregnancy, respectively.
Others have found similar middle cerebral artery blood flow changes with ultrasound .
Mechanisms and significance of the decline are unknown.
It appears that pregnancy does not affect cerebrovascular autoregulation .
# Memory.
Women often report problems with attention, concentration, and memory throughout pregnancy and the early puerperium.
Systematic studies of memory in pregnancy, however, are limited and often anecdotal.
In a metaanalysis, Davies and coworkers (2018) reported pregnancy-related memory decline was worst in the third trimester.
This decline was not attributable to depression, anxiety, sleep deprivation, or other physical changes associated with pregnancy.
It was transient and quickly resolved following delivery.
In follow up studies, preeclampsia and eclampsia were found to lead to both short- and long-term cognitive disability (Aukes, 2007; Dayan, 2018).
# Eyes.
Intraocular pressure declines during pregnancy and is attributed partly to greater vitreous outflow.
Corneal sensitivity is decreased, and the greatest changes are late in gestation.
Most pregnant women demonstrate a measurable but slight increase in corneal thickness, thought to be due to edema.
Consequently, they may have difficulty with previously comfortable contact lenses.
Brownish-red opacities on the posterior surface of the cornea —Krukenberg spindles—are observed with a higher than expected frequency during pregnancy.
Hormonal effects similar to those observed for skin lesions are believed to cause this increased pigmentation.
Other than transient loss of accommodation reported during both pregnancy and lactation, visual function is unaffected by pregnancy.
These changes during pregnancy and pathological eye aberrations were reviewed by Gilbert and colleagues (2019).
# Sleep.
Beginning as early as 12 weeks’ gestation and extending through the first 2 months postpartum, women have difficulty with falling asleep, frequent awakenings, fewer hours of night sleep, and reduced sleep efficiency.
These symptoms are part of the spectrum of sleep-disordered breathing, the most severe of which is obstructive sleep apnea (Ayyar, 2018; Dominguez, 2018).
The greatest disruption of sleep is encountered postpartum and may contribute to postpartum blues or to frank depression and suicidal ideation .